A Finding Aid to the Esta Nesbitt Papers, circa 1942-1981, in the Archives of American Art AAA.nesbesta
Archives of American Art
- Xerography Research Files, circa 1966-1974; Series 4; 2.5 Linear feet Box 2-4, 11, OV 16
  - Notebooks (Box 2)
    - Xerox Xplore Chroma-Capsagraphy, 1971 May-1972 January; "Xerox Xplore / chroma-capsagraphy / May 3.1971" (Box 3, Folder 11-12)
      Oversized material for Folder 12 housed in Box 11, Folder 3.
  - Notes, 1970-1972 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    Oversized material housed in Box 11, Folder 4.
  - Notes, 1971 July 7; 1972 April 8 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Slides and Transparencies (Box 3)
    - Experiments and Works in Progress, circa 1971 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Completed Prints, circa 1971 (Box 3, Folder 16-17)
  - Xerography Studies, 1967 June 14 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Xerography Studies 3M Preliminary Notes and Reference Materials, circa 1969 (Box 3, Folder 19-21)
  - Xerography Studies, 1970 December 11 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Xerography Studies Xerox Process Information, circa 1971 (Box 3, Folder 23-24)
  - Xerography Studies, 1971 February 8 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Xerography Studies, 1971 February 18 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Xerography Studies, 1971 February 25 (Box 3, Folder 27-28)
  - Xerography Studies, 1971 March 11 (Box 3, Folder 29-30)
    Oversized material housed in Box 11, Folder 5.
  - Xerography Studies, 1971 March 25 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Xerography Studies, 1971 April 1 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Xerography Studies, 1971 April 8 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Xerography Studies, 1971 April 12-22 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    Oversized material housed in Box 11, Folder 6.
  - Xerography Studies, 1971 April 22-29 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Xerography Studies, 1971 April 29 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Xerography Studies, 1971 May 6 (Box 3, Folder 37-39)
  - Xerography Studies, 1971 June 3 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Xerography Studies, 1971 June 17 (Box 4, Folder 2-7)
    Oversized material for Folder 7 housed in Box 11, Folder 6.
  - Xerography Studies, 1971 June 24 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Xerography Studies, 1971 July 8 (Box 4, Folder 9-12)
  - Xerography Studies, 1971 July 22 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Xerography Studies, 1971 July 29 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Xerography Studies, 1971 September 9 (Box 4, Folder 15-16)
  - Xerography Studies “Book of the Elevens”, 1971 September 9 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Xerography Studies Self Portraits, 1971 September 9 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Xerography Studies Book VI, 1971 September 16 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Xerography Studies for Extensions Show, 1971 November 30 (Box 4, Folder 20-21)
  - Xerography Studies “The Horse’s Dream”, 1972 March (Box 4, Folder 22)
    Oversized material housed in Box 11, Folder 7.
  - Xerography Studies, 1972 March (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Xerography Studies “Map of Mind”, 1972 April 16 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Xerography Studies, 1972 May 25 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Xerography Studies, 1971 June 3; 1972 August–November (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Xerography Studies, 1972 November 14 (Box 4, Folder 27-28)
    Oversized material housed in Box 11, Folder 8.
  - Xerography Studies, 1974 February 26 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Oversized Magazines, 1970-1971 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    Oversized material from Box 2, Folder 27.
  - Oversized Notebook, Xerox Xplore Chroma-Capsagraphy, 1971 May-1972 January (Box 11, Folder 3)
    Oversized material from Box 3, Folder 12.
  - Oversized Notes, 1970-1972 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    Oversized material from Box 3, Folder 13.
  - Oversized Notes, 1972 April 8; 1971 July 7 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    Oversized material from Box 3, Folder 14.
  - Oversized Xerography Studies, 1971 March 11 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    Oversized material from Box 3, Folders 29 and 30.
  - Oversized Xerography Studies, 1971 April 12-22 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    Oversized material from Box 3, Folder 34.
  - Oversized Xerography Studies, 1971 June 17 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    Oversized material from Box 4, Folder 7.
  - Oversized Xerography Studies, 1971 June 3; 1972 August–November (Box 11, Folder 6)
    Oversized material from Box 4, Folder 26.
  - Oversized Xerography Studies, 1972 March (Box 11, Folder 7)
    Oversized material from Box 4, Folder 22.
  - Oversized Xerography Studies, 1972 November 14 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    Oversized material from Box 4, Folders 27 and 28.
  - Oversized Clippings, circa 1970 (Box OV 16)
    Oversized material from Box 2, Folder 26.
- Project and Exhibition Files, circa 1966-1981; Series 5; 5.1 Linear feet Box 4-8, 11, 13, OV 17-19
  Series is arranged alphabetically by project or exhibition and then by format. Most of the film reels are arranged numerically, based on Nesbitt’s notations.
  Additional documents related to the projects and exhibitions documented in this series can be found in the Correspondence, Writings, Xerography Research Files, and Printed Material series. Documentation about an anti-war exhibit at Parsons School of Design is found in the Biographical Materials series.
  The Projects and Exhibitions series contains a variety of materials related to Nesbitt’s books, exhibitions, films, performance and participatory art, and other projects. The bulk of material in the series documents Nesbitt’s major multimedia works, and her Xerography and Shadow Paintings exhibitions. Types of documentation are listed under the project or exhibition title, and include correspondence, annotated clippings, microfilm, notes, sketches and diagrams, tape transcripts, motion picture film, sound recordings, photographs, publicity, and source material.
  The piece Walk up-Tape on is documented with notes, photographs, and xerography. The one reel of microfilm contains documentation mostly related to Walk up-Tape on. Many, but not all, of the documents reproduced in the microfilm are found in the collection.
  Nesbitt’s film and sound performance piece titled “Everyman as Anyman, or Putting On, On, On, On, On,” seems to have been performed as a multichannel projection of silent, super 8 mm films projected with as many as five stationary and moving film projectors alongside multilayered sound recordings. The motion picture film and sound recordings consist of 26 reels of Super 8 film and four sound tape reels. Film and sound reels are all numbered; note that there is no reel 2 in the collection. Visual content is a wide array of abstract imagery, text, solid color frames, artwork, and split screen imagery, and ranges from three to five second shots to much longer shots. The sound track also contains narrative elements. Additional details about the content of the film and sound reels can be found in the notebooks for this project, and details about how the reels were projected for various performances are found in the notebook labeled “Everyman Projections.” Source material for “Everyman” consists of words written on a variety of material, including paper towels, toilet paper, index cards, and foam boards.
  The film “Light Times 499,” created with Anibal Ambert, consists of a sequence of xerographic prints from Nesbitt’s serial work of the same title. Film and sound recordings consist of two reels of 16mm film and one sound cassette. One of the film reels contains splices, and the other appears to be a print of the spliced film. The cassette is labeled “preliminary soundtrack.”
  The series also contains documentation about the film “Folding/Struck,” but not the film itself.
  Various materials related to exhibitions document the creation of works through the installation of exhibition to the exhibition itself. Exhibitions of Nesbitt’s xerography work include “Electrostatic Structures: ‘New Morphs,’” “Electroworks,” “Esta Nesbitt: Xerography Prints,” and “Xerography – Extensions in Art.” Other exhibitions include the participatory exhibition “1000 Empty 49.3 Grams: A participatory environment” and Nesbitt’s exhibition of Shadow Paintings.
  Other projects documented in this series include a book entitled Poems of War and Revolution, a manuscript entitled “Sea of Movement,” and an illustrated journal entitled “Shadow and Pathways.”
  - “Annual New England Exhibition” at Silvermine Guild (between 1966-1969), Contact Sheets, circa 1966 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - “Electrostatic Structures: ‘New Morphs’” (1972-1973) (Box 4)
    - Contact Sheets of Exhibit, circa 1973 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Photographs of Exhibit, circa 1973 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Photographs of Source Material, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Press Material, circa 1972 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Price List and Labels for Artwork, 1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Slides of Exhibit, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - Xerography of Eyes, circa 1971 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - “Electroworks” at George Eastman House (1979-1981), Loan Agreement and Press Material (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - “Esta Nesbitt: Xerography Prints” (1976), Photographs of Exhibit, circa 1976 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - "Everyman as Anyman, or Putting On, On, On, On, On" (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Motion Picture Film, 1969; 4 Film reels Super 8 (Box 4, Folder 41-42)
    - Motion Picture Film (continued), 1969; 22 Film reels Super 8 (Box 5, Folder 1-11)
    - Film Announcement, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Notebook, circa 1969; "Silver book - June '69" (Box 5, Folder 13)
      Oversized material housed in OV 17.
    - Notebook of Everyman Projections, 1969; Transcribed from notebook cover: "'Everyman' projections - from July 8 - 1969 -" (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Notebook regarding Soundtrack, circa 1969; "Sound Track Notes / Everyman" (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Notebook regarding Soundtrack and Film Reel Information, 1969; Transcribed from notebook cover: "Film Everyman Notes continued: soundtrack & Burnt Zeroxes / Spring 69 / Intermedia / Film Sequences for editing" (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Photographic Material, circa 1969 (Box 6, Folder 2-3)
      Oversized material for Folder 3 housed in OV 17.
    - Project Statement, circa 1969 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Soundtrack, 1969; 4 sound tape reels (Box 6, Folder 5-8)
    - Source Material, circa 1969 (Box 6, Folder 9-20)
      Oversized material for Folder 9 housed in OV 18. Oversized material for Folders 13 and 14 housed in OV 17.
    - Source Material (continued), circa 1969 (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
  - "Folding/Struck" (Box 7)
    - Notes, 1970; Transcribed from notebook cover: "Jan 31.70 / Film 'Folding:Struck'" (Box 7, Folder 3)
      Oversized material housed in Box 11, Folder 9.
    - Photographic Material, circa 1970 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Printed Material, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - "Light Times 499" (Box 7)
    - Film by Anibal Ambert, circa 1972; 2 Film reels 16mm (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Photographic Material, circa 1972 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Preliminary Soundtrack by Anibal Ambert, 1971; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - “Memorial Exhibition of Drawing and Illustrations by Esta Nesbitt” (1977), Contact Sheets (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - New York: Hold It!, Press Release and Kit, circa 1972 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - “1000 Empty 49.3 Grams: A participatory environment” (1970) (Box 7)
    - Black Box, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Contact Sheets, circa 1970 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Guestbook, 1970-1971 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Journals, 1969-1970; "Black Boxes" / July 30 '70 "Black Boxes" / Dec 2/70 (Box 7, Folder 14-16)
    - Notes, 1970-1971 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Paintings, Photographic Material, circa 1966 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Poems of War and Revolution (Box 7)
    - Source Material and Drafts, circa 1970 (Box 7, Folder 19-21)
    - Installation Documents, circa 1970 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Sea of Movement, circa 1967 (Box 7, Folder 23-24)
  - Shadow and Pathways, Illustrated Journal, 1964-1967; Transcribed from journal cover: "SHADOW" & PATHWAYS" ETC. 1966-1967 (Box 7, Folder 25)
    Oversized material housed in Box 13 and OV 19.
  - Shadow Paintings (Box 7)
    - Contact Sheets of Installation, circa 1974 (Box 7, Folder 26)
    - Illustrated Journal, 1966-1967; "shadow ptgs - color swatches etc / 1966/1967" (Box 7, Folder 27)
    - Illustrated Journal, 1973; "shadows May 1973 - For Exhibition WestBdwy" (Box 7, Folder 28)
    - Negatives of Artwork, circa 1974 (Box 7, Folder 29)
    - Notebook, 1970-1971; Transcribed from notebook cover: Aug 9-70 - / shadow ptg / Summer 1970 - / Xerox Xplore / April 17.1971 / Xerox Xplore plans - new ideas for 1972-1973 (Box 7, Folder 30)
    - Notes, 1970-1974 (Box 7, Folder 31)
    - Photograph Album of Works in Progress and Installation, circa 1974 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Photographic Material of Works in Progress, circa 1970 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Photographs of Artwork, circa 1967-circa 1972 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Photographs of Artwork, circa 1974 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Photographs of Exhibit, circa 1974 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Printed Material, circa 1967-circa 1973 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Transparencies of Exhibit, 1974 (Box 8, Folder 7-8)
  - Unidentified film, undated; 1 Film reels Super 8 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Unidentified sound recording, circa 1970; 1 sound tape reels (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Walk Up – Tape On (Box 8)
    - Correspondence, 1969-1972 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Funding Application, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Microfilm Record of Documents, 1969-1971 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Notes, 1969-1972; "Nov 15-69 / Take my place - (stand in for me -)" (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Notes on Street Works, circa 1970; "Sound Mar 10.70 for experimental tape / STREET WORKS Mar 21/70" (Box 8, Folder 15-16)
    - Photographic Material, circa 1969 (Box 8, Folder 17-18)
      Oversized material for Folder 17 housed in Box 11, Folder 10.
    - Project Statement, circa 1973 (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Transcript of Conversation with David Levy, 1969-1970 (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Xerography, circa 1970 (Box 8, Folder 21-22)
  - “Xerography - Extensions in Art” (1971-1972) (Box 8)
    - All the Lines are Nines, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 23)
    - Big Eyes, circa 1971 (Box 8, Folder 24)
    - Exhibit Diagrams, circa 1971 (Box 8, Folder 25)
    - Journal, 1971; "XEROX EXHIBITION - Book I / Aug 12-71 - Oct 25.71" (Box 8, Folder 26-27)
    - Journal, 1971-1972; "XEROX EXHIBITION - Book II / Oct-25.71 - Feb 28 '72" (Box 8, Folder 28-30)
    - Notes, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 31)
    - Photograph Album of Exhibit, circa 1971 (Box 8, Folder 32)
    - Photographic Material, circa 1970 (Box 8, Folder 33)
    - Press Material, circa 1971 (Box 8, Folder 34)
      Oversized material housed in OV 19.
  - Oversized from "Folding/Struck", Notes, 1970 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    Oversized material from Box 7, Folder 3.
  - Oversized from "Folding/Struck", Printed Material, 1970 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    Oversized material from Box 7, Folder 5.
  - Oversized from "Light Times 499", Photographic Material, circa 1972 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    Oversized material from in Box 7, Folder 7.
  - Oversized from “1000 Empty 49.3 Grams: A participatory environment” (1970), Notes, 1970-1971 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    Oversized material from Box 7, Folder 17.
  - Oversized from Shadow Paintings, Photographs of Exhibit, circa 1974 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    Oversized material from Box 8, Folder 5.
  - Oversized from Walk Up – Tape On, Photographic Material, circa 1969 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    Oversized material from Box 8, Folder 17.
  - Oversized from Shadow and Pathways, Illustrated Journal, 1964-1967 (Box 13)
    Oversized material from Box 7, Folder 25.
  - Oversized from "Everyman as Anyman, or Putting On, On, On, On, On" Notebook, circa 1969 (Box OV 17)
    Oversized material from Box 5, Folder 13.
  - Oversized from "Everyman as Anyman, or Putting On, On, On, On, On", Notebook regarding Soundtrack, circa 1969 (Box OV 17)
    Oversized material from Box 5, Folder 15.
  - Oversized from "Everyman as Anyman, or Putting On, On, On, On, On", Photographic Material, circa 1969 (Box OV 17)
    Oversized material from Box 6, Folder 3.
  - Oversized from "Everyman as Anyman, or Putting On, On, On, On, On", Source Material, circa 1969 (Box OV 17)
    Oversized material from Box 6, Folders 13 and 14.
  - Oversized from "Everyman as Anyman, or Putting On, On, On, On, On", Source Material, circa 1969 (Box OV 18)
    Oversized material from Box 6, Folder 9.
  - Oversized form Shadow and Pathways, Illustrated Journal, 1964-1967 (Box OV 19)
  - Oversized from “Xerography - Extensions in Art” (1971-1972), Press Material, circa 1971 (Box OV 19)
    Oversized material from Box 8, Folder 34.
- Printed Material, circa 1963-1977; 1942-circa 1944; Series 6; 0.9 Linear feet Box 9-10, OV 20
  Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs include group and individual exhibitions. They are arranged based on Nesbitt’s involvement with the exhibition and the medium of Nesbitt’s work.
  Additional printed material is found throughout the collection.
  Printed Material contains books, catalogs, clippings, exhibition announcements, posters, magazines, and press releases. Included are published listings, reviews, and images of Nesbitt’s work and exhibitions, and some of the clippings on xerography feature Nesbitt. The rest of the material reflects Nesbitt’s interests, dealing with Chinese and Japanese literature, color, communication, creation and duplication of images electronically, energy, film, hallucinogenic experiences, painting, street works, and xerography. In comparison to the rest of the collection, the material in this series has little to no annotations; however, the book and magazine on film are heavily annotated.
  - Books (Box 9)
    - Readings in American Art Since 1900: A Documentary Survey, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - An Introduction to the American Underground Film, 1967 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Who Am I? (NĀN YĀR?) of Bhagavan Sri Ramana Maharshi, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Catalogs (Box 9)
    - Children Books, 1964-1966 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Children Books, 1969-1970 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Parsons School of Design, 1974-1975 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Clippings (Box 9)
    - Art, Communication, and Computers, 1968-circa 1972 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Arts College, 1970 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Book Excerpts and Reviews, 1970-1973 (Box 9, Folder 9)
      Oversized material housed in OV 20.
    - Color, circa 1963 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Nesbitt’s Exhibitions and Works, 1970-1974 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Painting, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Entropy, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - World War II, circa 1944 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Xerox and Xerography, circa 1966-circa 1974 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Exhibition Announcements (Box 9)
    - Nesbitt’s Exhibitions, 1967-1977 (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Other Artists, 1973 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Exhibition Catalogs (Box 10)
    - Nesbitt’s Paintings, Drawings and Prints, 1966 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Nesbitt’s Paintings, Drawings and Prints, 1967 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Nesbitt’s Paintings, Drawings and Prints, 1968 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Nesbitt’s Xerography, 1971 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Nesbitt’s Xerography, 1976; 1973 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Other Artists, 1942; 1971 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Exhibition Posters, circa 1973 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Magazines (Box 10)
    - Art and Exhibition Listings, 1970; 1974 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Film, Color, and Electronic Image Creation, 1969-1970 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Newspaper of Visual Studies Workshop, 1973 May (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Press Releases, 1970-1975 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Student Publication of Parsons School of Design, 1974 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Technical Publication titled Ultraviolet and Fluorescence Photography, circa 1968 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Television Script titled “Doctor Einstein Before Lunch”, 1973 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Oversized Clippings, Book Excerpts and Reviews, 1970-1973 (Box OV 20)
    Oversized material from Box 9, Folder 9.
  - Oversized Clippings, Nesbitt's Exhibitions and Works, 1970-1974 (Box OV 20)
    Oversized material from Box 9, Folder 12.
  - Oversized Clippings, World War II, circa 1944 (Box OV 20)
    Oversized material from Box 9, Folder 14.
  - Oversized Clippings, Xerox and Xerography, circa 1966-circa 1974 (Box OV 20)
    Oversized material from Box 9, Folder 15.
  - Oversized Exhibition Announcements, Nesbitt's Exhibitions, 1967-1977 (Box OV 20)
    Oversized material from Box 9, Folder 16.
  - Oversized Exhibition Posters, circa 1973 (Box OV 20)
    Oversized material from Box 10, Folder 8.
  - Oversized Magazines; Film, Color, and Electronic Image Creation, 1969-1970 (Box OV 20)
    Oversized material from Box 10, Folder 10.
  - Oversized Newspaper of Visual Studies Workshop, 1973 May (Box OV 20)
    Oversized material from Box 10, Folder 11.